Guide to the Carolyn S. Schumacher Papers AIS.2011.09
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- History of College Women in Pittsburgh Research File, 1970-1999; 1986-1988; IV.
  - Oral History Project: Cassette Tapes, 1986-1988; 4.
    - Christine E. Greco, April 28; May 7, 1988 (Box 6, Cassette 6-7)
      Christine Greco was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 180 minutes. Greco discussed early family life, business, and her early education at the Dennison School (Swissvale), Wilkins School, and Swissvale High School in Pittsburgh. Greco attended the University of Pittsburgh where she received a partial scholarship and majored in German with minors in English, Italian, and Latin aiming of teaching German. Greco speaks of her "startling experience" with a sex education class taught by Dr. Jameson during her time at Pitt. She also notes the changing expectations in the way women dressed during the time and speaks about the limited job market caused by the depression and both World Wars. Greco recalled her first full time job at Gimbels and attending the School of Retailing, paid for by Gimbels.
    - Elizabeth McDonald, April 20, 1988 (Box 6, Cassette 8)
      Elizabeth McDonald was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 90 minutes. McDonald discussed her early life living in Pittsburgh, including memories about bootlegging in her neighborhood. McDonald recalled family life and her education at the Conroy School (Kindergarten- 8th Grade) and graduation from Allegheny High School in 1926. Although her father did not support her decision, McDonald continued her education with the Frick Training School, graduated second in her class in 1929, and found a job quickly in teaching. McDonald taught at Cowley, Manchester, Lemington, and Linton before becoming a supervisor and then a principle while also teaching veterans in the evening.
    - Florence Marcus, June 1986 (Box 6, Cassette 9)
      Florence Marcus was interviewed for approximately 47 minutes about her career path and experiences. Marcus graduated from the University of Pittsburgh in 1929 and pursued practicing medicine. Marcus reflects on the difficulty of being hired as a Jewish female. Originally became a nurse and worked for ten years, but decided to go to medical school. Marcus recalled her male classmates' fondness toward her due to her previous experiences as a nurse and her success in class work. Marcus first worked at Montefiore, then Shadyside Hospital, and finally opened a family practice in 1930. Due to the depression, Marcus was not receiving many payments for her visits, so she got a job with another doctor examining school children in Pittsburgh; following this experience she attended Harvard's School of Public Health in 1949. Finally, she worked as a general practitioner for social work cases at St. Francis Hospital.
    - Frances Holland, November 18 and 27, 1987 (Box 6, Cassette 10-11)
      Fran Holland was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 45 minutes about her life and career experiences. In 1968, Holland became the first Dean of Students for La Roche College and began attracting mature young women from 20-40 years old who had children and wanted to go back to school. A year later, President Blum of Point Park College hired her as the Director of Development where Holland raised funds to build the new library. She then became the Director of Admissions and later the Director of College and Community Relations. Holland proudly discussed her volunteerism including working with the Girl Scouts and being the President of the Allegheny County Scholarship Association, and the Civil Service Commission. Holland recalls memories of Thrysa Amos whom she met at the age of 11 and continued to work with closely until Amos's death in 1941.
    - Helen Hackett, November 7 and 11, 1988 (Box 6, Cassette 12-13)
      Helen Hackett was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 133 minutes concerning her early education, family, and college experiences. Hackett recalls growing up in Brushton and moving to Wilkinsburg for high school. Hackett took secretarial courses at Margaret Morrison (Carnegie Tech), married in 1930, and her daughter was born in 1933. Hackett worked as dean of women at Carnegie Tech/ Margaret Morrison for two years, and then took a job at the Carnegie Library. Hackett speaks of the changing religious expectations of women during the period in addition to her life experiences.
    - Helen Poole Rush, October 30; November 11, 1985 (Box 6, Cassette 14-16)
      Hellen Poole Rush was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 180 minutes concerning her education, work, and life experiences. Rush entered the University of Pittsburgh in 1915 and recalled memories of people she attended school with and later, recollections of students who attended Pitt while she was working there. Rush discussed the expectations for freshmen students to transform from boys and girls to young women and men during their first semester. She discusses Lantern night as essential in this transformation for women, and explains the mythology and ceremony associated with it. Additionally, Rush discusses the Senior Queen Ceremony and the Caritas Ceremony as important to the development of young women during their college years. Rush goes on to discuss the philosophical evolution of the department of the Dean of Women at the University of Pittsburgh.
    - Helen Sawyer, May 27, 1988 (Box 6, Cassette 17)
      Helen Sawyer was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 90 minutes concerning her life educational experiences. Sawyer received her Bachelor's degree in Physical Education from the University of Pittsburgh (1934) and her Master of Education from the University of Pittsburgh. She reflects on people she knew, organizations, and rules imposed on women by administration but especially by themselves. Sawyer became the first female gym teacher at Etna High School. After getting married (1938) and having children, Sawyer began teaching again.
    - Irene Pasinski, April 25, 1988 (Box 6, Cassette 18)
      Irene Pasinski was interviewed for approximately 70 minutes by Carolyn Schumacher. Pasinski discussed her Polish immigrant parents, early education, and family structure. Pasinski's father worked Polish Consulate in Pittsburgh until 1941 when the Polish government fell. She reflects upon the differences between educational understanding in the United States and in Europe and how that could have affected her educational experience. Pasinski attended Schenley High School and went to Carnegie Mellon to pursue a degree in industrial design with a minor in painting. She recalls her extra-curricular experiences in Chi Omega recruiting other members. Five years after graduation, Pasinski received a Fulbright Scholarship to study and teach in France; she and her husband stayed in Europe until they divorced. Pasinski speaks about Polish immigrant groups and the determination to break the Slavic stereotype.
    - Janet MacDonald Flinn, June 29, 1988 (Box 6, Cassette 19)
      Janet MacDonald Flinn was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 90 minutes. Flinn recalls her family life, early education, and career choices. She attended the University of Pittsburgh where, in 1917, she won a school medal for the debating team, became one of the first female mortar board students, and graduated in 1918. She taught English in the Irwin School District, and then taught at the Thurston School. Flinn married in 1920 and shares her thoughts about being a woman during the time period.
    - Jean Phipps Bray, May 24, 1988 (Box 6, Cassette 20)
      Jean Phipps Bray was interviewed for approximately 80 minutes concerning her family life, early education, and experience as a woman in education. Bray attended Winchester-Thurston Girls Preparatory School and graduated in 1939, and attended a Junior College in Washington DC before attempting to transfer to the University of Pittsburgh. After the University of Pittsburgh refused to accept Junior College credit, she became interested in Carnegie Mellon University in 1941. Speaks about her experiences at Carnegie Mellon and reflects upon her education and career.
    - Lillian Brest, December 18, 1987; January 6, 1988 (Box 7, Cassette 1-2)
      Lillian Brest was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 120 minutes. Brest shares information about her Jewish family, including Lithuanian parents who immigrated to the United States. Brest attended Chelsea High School and participated as a member of the debate society and in theater. She then went to Simmons College to study Social Service Work, because she liked the idea of having a year of practicum before graduation in 1922. Afterward, she felt she was not 'tough enough' for a career in Social Service, and regretted some of her choices. Brest discusses married life and children on their Norfolk, Massachusetts farm during the depression.
    - Mary Ann Aug, 1987 (Box 7, Cassette 3)
      Mary Ann Aug discussed her career path in an interview with Monique Savits for approximately 40 minutes. As an undergraduate, Aug took courses in English literature, writing, journalism, public relations, and publications writing, but decided to stick to Public Relations writing because of the topical flexibility. Aug became the Director of University Relations at the University of Pittsburgh and discusses the job in depth. Additionally, she spoke about the differences between women and men within the University, the professional field, and mentions examples of sexual discrimination she has faced.
    - Mary Briscoe, undated (Box 7, Cassette 4)
      Mary Briscoe was interviewed for approximately 50 minutes by Linda J. Beater concerning her career path and professional choices. Briscoe is the Dean of the College of Arts and Sciences for the University of Pittsburgh working to assist in undergraduate advising and programming. Briscoe described her job obligations and the differences between women and men in her field and at the University.
    - Mary Cole, March 30; April 13, 1988 (Box 7, Cassette 5-6)
      Mary Cole was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 60 minutes. Cole attended elementary and high school in Butler, PA. Education was important to Cole's mother, who was a teacher, and Cole chose to attend Chatham College after she received a half scholarship. At Chatham, Cole majored in science and worked with the National Youth Administration, making $0.50 an hour. Following graduation, Cole taught in her High School, but then decided to enroll in the Army. She graduated from Officer Candidate School on October 3, 1942, becoming only the thirteenth woman from Pittsburgh to achieve the feat. Cole spoke about the excitement and adventure provided by her experiences in the Army, the opportunity to go to the University of Pittsburgh for graduate school through the GI Bill, flying lessons, and about her perception of discrimination against women.
    - Maureen Greenwald, December 8, 1986 (Box 7, Cassette 7)
      Maureen Greenwald was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 45 minutes concerning her involvement in and development of the Women's Studies Program at the University of Pittsburgh. Greenwald discussed the difficulties of creating and editing the program, while still building a strong base during development. She spoke of the changes experienced by the Women's Studies Program and its goals since its inception.
    - Opening the Gallery, Dr. Posvar & Goldie, undated (Box 7, Cassette 8)
      This tape documenting the gallery opening for the exhibit, "The History of Women at Pitt: Reflections on a Changing Society" and runs approximately 55 minutes. The majority of the tape is conversations happening in the gallery; some people discuss the exhibit, while others speak of their experience as females at the University of Pittsburgh. Additionally, Carolyn Schumacher addressed those in attendance to thank the committee which developed the exhibit and the production team. Monique Simms spoke about female achievement at the University of Pittsburgh.
    - Peg Covert, December 22, 1986 (Box 7, Cassette 9)
      Peg Covert was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 65 minutes about her career path and chosen field. Covert began working at the University of Pittsburgh in 1946 as an assistant professor, in the Cathedral of Learning. She spoke fondly of her experiences teaching athletics, including field hockey and the inception of cheerleading at the University. Covert pronounced the importance of physical education for women during the time period and today.
    - Rachel Donaldson, June 7, 1988 (Box 7, Cassette 10)
      Rachael Donaldson was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 90 minutes. Donaldson discussed her family, lack of money, and early education. Originally, she attended Indiana State College, but transferred to Chatham where she studied Latin and French, joined a language club, and graduated in 1936. After graduation, Donaldson worked at the Junior High School in Moon Run teaching social studies and English, and then she moved to Coraopolis to teach Latin and French. Donaldson then received at job working at the University of Pittsburgh's Alumni Office, and decided to pursue a Masters of Education degree. Donaldson joined the Waves and was sent to Newport and Boston Navy Yards where she attended Court Marshal cases and taught Naval Law. Following the war, she moved to Aspinwall, married in 1947, and started having a family.
    - Savina Skewis, October 17, 1986 (Box 7, Cassette 11)
      Savina Skewis was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 65 minutes. Skewis graduated from the University of Delaware in 1927, with a major in home economics and a minor in chemistry. In 1946, Skewis began working at the University of Pittsburgh as Assistant Director of Food Services. She explained her interest in food as it relates to people and the development of families. Skewis spoke of her experience on the 12th Floor of the Cathedral of Learning, helping with dinners, teas, and attending meetings. Skewis discussed a time line of her career including becoming the Associate Dean of Women in 1950, Dean of Women in 1968, Associate Dean of Students in 1971, Advisor to the Chancellor and Director of Heinz Chapel from 1974-1978, and finally, the Consultant to the Secretary of the University from 1978-1984.
    - Schumacher Interviewed by Joe Desteo at KQV Radio about History of Women at Pitt, 1987 (Box 7, Cassette 12)
      Carolyn Schumacher is interviewed on KQV Radio by Desteo for approximately 20 minutes. Schumacher speaks about the exhibit "The History of Women at Pitt: Reflections on a Changing Society" while also giving general information about female education during the late 1800s- early 1900s. Schumacher speaks about her research, sources, oral history interviews, and production of the exhibit. Additionally, she speaks about the impact of both World Wars on the educational and occupational opportunities for women.
    - Schumacher Interview with WTAE, 1987 (Box 7, Cassette 13)
      Carolyn Schumacher is interviewed by John O'Malley of WEEP FM Radio for approximately 23 minutes. Schumacher discusses the development of "The History of Women at Pitt: Reflections on a Changing Society" in addition to her research, sources, oral history interviews, and gives general information about opportunities for women during the twentieth century.
    - Sunny Pickering, April 12, 1988 (Box 7, Cassette 14)
      Sunny Pickering was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 60 minutes. She speaks of her family life, parent's education, and early education experiences. Pickering attended Rochelle Elementary School while also attending oratory school and art classes; she graduated from Carrick High School in 1938. Pickering spoke of the importance of getting her driver's license and living through the depression. Her family believed she needed polishing, so they sent her to Allegheny College in Meadville to learn manners, social graces, and to experience living away from home. In 1939, she transferred to Carnegie Institute of Technology/ Margaret Morrison to study art; while in college, she joined Alpha Kappa Psi and met her husband.
    - Carolyn Sutton, March 4; March 9, 1988 (Box 7, Cassette 15-16)
      Carolyn Sutton was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 90 minutes about her childhood, family, and early education experiences. Sutton grew up in Sewickley, attended Sewickley Academy, and then was sent away to the Master's Boarding School in New York. Sutton then attended the University of Pittsburgh, studying "general education," language, English, and art. Sutton recalled memories of communist students, African American classmates, and going before the Senior Court for failing her orientation exam. Sutton worked in a machine shop in Bellevue making "go-no-go gauges" earning $0.90-$1.10; she spoke of her experience as the only woman in the machine shop and the friendships she built.
    - Terri Gould, undated (Box 7, Cassette 17)
      Terry Gould was interviewed by Debora (?) for approximately 28 minutes concerning her career path. Gould, who speaks about her experience as the Director of Educational and Community Affairs at the University of Pittsburgh, discusses her job role, professional obligations, and early familial expectations. Gould mentioned her exposure to sexual discrimination and experiences, as compared to men, in the field.
    - Vee Toner, November 24, 1987 (Box 7, Cassette 18)
      Vee Toner was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 60 minutes concerning her early family life, education, and experiences as a woman growing up in the twentieth century. Toner's father started the Lackzoom Health Food Stores in Pittsburgh, which became GNC (General Nutrition Centers) after her brother took over the business. Toner attended the University of Pittsburgh, which she believed to be co-educational and welcoming to women. At Pitt, Toner studied Liberal Arts, joined Delta Zeta, and participated in the sophomore honorary organization Quains(?). As a young woman, Toner owned her own plane and flew in air races and contests. Toner also attended the University of Wisconsin and UCLA to gain Physical Education credits to become a basketball coach in addition to teaching physical education and health, which she did for ten years. Toner married in 1937 and moved often for her husband's job with PPG.
    - Viola Pattersons, December 10, 1986 (Box 7, Cassette 19)
      Viola Pattersons was interviewed by Carolyn Schumacher for approximately 63 minutes. Pattersons recalled her years at the University of Pittsburgh studying education, and mentions skipping class in order to go out to the lawn (where the Cathedral of Learning is now) to watch Billy Sunday speak from a tent. Pattersons graduated and began teaching 8th grade history for $68 a week.
- Legal File, 1883-1933; V.
  Series IV contains legal documents from the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. There appears to be no obvious relationship between the records and Schumacher's personal life or research.
  - Artisans' Insurance Co. vs Burgy, 1892-1895 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Foster Shop vs. Geraldine Brown Duvall, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Rea & Co. vs. Scully and Co., 1883-1884 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - South Hills Hardware Co. vs Anna K. Schmied, 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Women at Pitt Research File, 1895-1986; VI.
  Series VI contains material related to Schumacher's research focusing on women at the University of Pittsburgh, from the acceptance of the first female students in 1895 to the inception of the Women's Studies Program in 1972. The series includes articles and publications, correspondence, legislation, newspaper clippings, and notes.
  - Affirmative Action, 1972-1986 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Agnes Lynch Starrett, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Allegheny Observatory, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Alumnae Association Brief History, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Alumnae Tally, 1894-1916 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "Among Our Alumnae", March, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Associated Women Students, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Beatrice Taylor, 1898 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Bibliography Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - "Black Women at Pitt", 1986 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Bleak House, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Blossom Henry, 1918-1944 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Braun Room, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Buildings, 1917-1986 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Bureau of Retail Training, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Campus Women's Organization, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Caritas Ceremony, 1940-1956 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Carol Kline, 1963-1986 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Carol Simko Christobek, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Cathedral of Learning, 1926-1937 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Chancellor's Report, 1894 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Chemistry Laboratory Admission of First Woman, 1892 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Chronology of University--1787-1938, c1940 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - "Co-eds", 1914 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Co-ed Prom, 1923-1938 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Continuing Education, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Courant, 1894-1897 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Curriculum, 1883-1904 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Dancing, Irregular, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Daniel Agnew, 1879-1885 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Dean of Women, 1912-1955 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Dean of Women Annual Reports, 1925-1945 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Department of News and Publications, 1945-1987 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Donna Jean Roberts, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Elizabeth Childs, undated (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Elizabeth Urey Baranger, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Enrollment, 1908-1965 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Evening School Association, 1926-1938 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Faculty Statistics, 1971-1979 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Female Alumni, 1915-1925 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Green Armband Ceremony, 1926-1938 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Heinz House, 1928-1944 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - "History of the Women at the University" by Jean Wright McLean, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - "History of Women at Pitt" by Jean Wright McLean, undated (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Honorary Degree, 1895-1916 (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Intercollegiate Association of Women, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Lantern Night, 1929-1983 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Law, 1894-1987 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Libraries, 1917-1936 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Luba Robin Goldsmith, undated (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Matilda Smith, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - "Mental and Physical Effects of Menstration" Thesis by Florence M. Teagarden, A.B., 1916 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Newspaper Clippings of Influential Women, 1919-1988 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Notes, people (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Notes, photographs (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - The Owl, 1905-1975 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Photograph List, undated (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Pitt Freshman Handbook, 1930-1931 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Pittiquette, 1943-1944 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Pitt Magazine Index, 1910-1939 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Polaris, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Questionnaire for 50th Anniversary of Women at Pitt, undated (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Radio, 1926-1928 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Rebell Yell (The), 1930 (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - Regional Campuses, 1919-1988 (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Residence Life, 1914-1970 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Reserve Officers' Training Corps (ROTC), 1936 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Ruth Conlogue Maszkiewicz, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Sara M. Soffel, 1952-1961 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - Sarah Rhodes Hauser, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Sharon Johnson, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Science, 1926-1946 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Significant Firsts for Women at Pitt, 1895-1987 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Scholarships, 1901-1902 (Box 8, Folder 75)